Downloading and installing Railway Operation Simulator makes no changes to the registry nor to any other operating system or user settings.  It does not require a complex installation procedure and does not have an uninstall program.  If it isn't wanted then just delete it, nothing else will be affected.  It was developed under Windows 10 using Embarcadero's C++ Builder compiler version 10.3.

***Important Note: Please don’t hide the Windows taskbar when running the program as it causes the screen to flash.  Why this should happen isn’t known at present.***

Unzipping file 'Release v2.11.1.zip' produces a folder named 'Railway', together with a user manual named 'Manual v2.11.0.pdf' (still valid for v2.11.1), a quick start guide named 'Quick start.pdf', this file 'readme.txt', and a folder named 'Metadata', explained below.

The 'Railway' folder should be moved to the location from where the program is to run, and must be a read/write location - i.e. somewhere on a hard disk or a memory stick, but not a CDRom.  For convenience, when the folder has been located, open up the folder and add a shortcut on the desktop to the main program file which is named 'railway.exe'.  This can be done by right clicking on the 'railway.exe' file icon in Windows Explorer, selecting 'Send To', then in the submenu selecting 'Desktop (create shortcut)'.  

Existing users should allow files in their existing 'Railway' folder to be replaced with new ones from the new folder.

We recommended printing 'Quick Start.pdf' (4 pages of A4) for reference during the first use of the program.  'Manual v2.11.0.pdf' is the program's help file in a single document which can also be printed if you wish - it's a 55 page A4 document - though the same information is available anytime from within the program via the 'Help' menu.

If you don't have a 'pdf' reader please go to http://get.adobe.com/uk/reader/ to download a free copy.

A lot more help is available from the website (www.railwayoperationsimulator.com) under the 'Help' tab.  There are two quickstart videos available and a more in-depth series of four videos produced by Keith Hazelton entitled 'Designing a Railway (with video)'.  They provide a detailed introduction to the program and are highly recommended.  Timetabling is the most difficult aspect to learn, so help is available in the form of an introduction and online tutorials under the 'Help' tab, and the tutorials are also downloadable under the 'Downloads & Projects' then 'Base Program' tabs.  Also downloadable is a detailed explanation of timetable error messages.

There is a very active Discord community where developing projects are discussed along with many other things associated with railways, and if additional help is needed it can easily be obtained by posting your problem in the 'helpdesk' channel. You are invited to sign up by clicking the 'Discord' tab on the website.

The Metadata folder contains two files, one for each of the two railways that come with the download - Birmingham and Liverpool.  The files are of type .toml - 'Tom's Obvious Minimal Language', which provides a format that is both human and computer-readable.  Going forward it is intended to make more use of computer file reading, so users are encouraged to provide these files with any new railways that they submit to the website.  More information about toml files can be found at https://toml.io/en/, and a list of country codes is provided at https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/#search/code.  

That's it - ready to go - we hope you like the program and find it useful.

Please let us know via Discord or the website how you get on with it - good points, bad points and any errors (hopefully few).

Best regards,

The ROS team